Land management survey, Navajo Indian Reservation reports, 1930-1938
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Land management survey, Navajo Indian Reservation reports, 1930-1938
AZ 124
United States. Soil Conservation Service,; McColm, George L.
This collection consists of manuscripts and preliminary reports relating to soil conservation, range conditions, crop production, timber and water resources on the Navajo Reservation during the 1930's.
2.0 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL:http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Historical Note
Organization
This collection is organized into 2 Series. Series 1 includes 18 subseries of reports and maps based on geographical units within the reservation. Series 2 consists of miscellaneous reports and maps.
Series 1: Navajo Reservation Units 1-18, ca.1930-1938
Series 2: Miscellaneous reports and maps, 1935-1941
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of 54 bound folders containing manuscripts and preliminary reports relating to the agronomy, soil and water conservation problems existing on the Navajo Reservation during the 1930's. The basis of this material is surveys made by the Soil Conservation Service. The material is arranged according to units based on geographical divisions within the reservation.
Access Terms
United States. Soil Conservation Service
Soil Conservation--Arizona
Soil Surveys--Navajo Indian Reservation
Rangelands--Navajo Indian Reservation
Range Management--Navajo Indian Reservation
Navajo Indian Reservation
Publications
Container List
- Series 1: Navajo Reservation geographical Units 1-18, ca.1930-1938
  - Subseries 1, Unit One ca.1930-1938
    Located in the northwestern area of the Navajo Indian Reservation, in Coconino County, Arizona, roughly between 36°45' north latitude and 110°45' and 111°30' west longitude.
    - Engineering Report, ca. 1930 (Box 1, Volume 1)
      Prepared by C.L. Moyes, Engineering Aide. Data on physical features, climate, vegetation, wildlife, agriculture, and mineral resources. Supplemented with sketch map of Cow Springs Irrigation Project. 41 pp., plus tables.
    - Agronomy Branch Report, 1937 (Box 1, Volume 2)
      Detailed report of conditions relating to agricultural land, crop production, suggestions for improvement of rangeland. 40 pp., plus tables.
    - Range Management Branch Report, May, 1937 (Box 1, Volume 3)
      Prepared by D.G. Anderson. Contains general description of land, past and present use of range, and range management objectives, as well as plans and recommendations for improvement of range. 87 pp., 2 tables.
    - Land Planning Report, January, 1938 (Box 1, Volume 4)
      Prepared by D.G. Anderson. Compilation of basic data from all field surveys by the various branches. Includes sections on effect of environment on human activity, land utilization, establishment of proper land use, and outlines a construction program to improve and conserve natural resources of Unit One. 102 pp., 3 tables, 2 sketches.
  - Subseries 2, Unit Two, 1938
    Northwestern portion of Navajo Reservation, between 36°15' and 37°15' north latitude and between 110°30' and 111°15' west longitude.
    - Engineering Report, January, 1938 (Box 1, Volume 5)
      Prepared by C.L. Moyes, Engineering Aide. Data on landforms, climate, vegetation, wildlife and agriculture and mineral resources. Supplement with "Report Sketch" (map) of Paiute Canyon Farms. 109 pp.
  - Subseries 3, Unit Three, ca. 1937-1938
    Extreme western section of Navajo Reservation, confines are approximately the 35°30' parallel on south, 36°45' parallel on north, the 111°45' meridian on west, and 111° meridian on the east.
    - Agronomy Branch Report, no date (Box 1, Volume 6)
      Relates to condition of Agricultural land, crop production, and suggestion for land improvement. Detailed information pertaining to Hopi and Paiute farming within area, as well as tabulation of population,. 33 pp., plus tables.
    - Range Management Branch Report, March 15, 1937 (Box 1, Volume 7)
      Prepared by D.G. Anderson. General description of land, past and present use of range and range management objectives, as well as plans and recommendations for improvement of range adjacent to Tuba City. Contains also a description of "Present Livestock Movement," which was obtained by questioning the Indians and consulting Social and Economic Division records.
    - Land Planning Report, January, 1938 (Box 1, Volume 8)
      Prepared by D.G. Anderson. Compilation of data from all field surveys conducted by soil conservationists. Includes detailed information on geography, climate, agricultural practices, potentials, as well as methods involved in "Establishment of Proper Land Use." 107 pp.
  - Subseries 4, Unit Four, ca. 1936-1937
    Land Management Unit 4 occupies parts of Navajo, Apache and Coconino counties in Arizona and lies in a southwestern direction between the 35°45' and 36°40' parallels of latitude, and the 109°45' and 111°0' meridians of longitude.
    - Agronomy Branch Report, no date (Box 2, Volume 9)
      Summary of agricultural locations and practice. Includes an itemized list of recommended projects which would, if carried out, help conserve and improve valuable farm land and methods.
    - Range Management Branch Report, December, 1936 (Box 2, Volume 10)
      Prepared by W.R. McKinny, Jr., Range Examiner. A compilation of surveys dealing with land utilization and improvement for Unit Four, lying wholly within the drainage area of the Little Colorado River, and occupying much of the Black Mesa Area. Includes 7 accompanying maps. (Duplicate copy)
    - Stock Water in Land Management District Four, no date (Box 2, Volume 11)
      Prepared as an explanation of water map (missing). Locates all water reserves of area capable of sustaining livestock.
    - Sub-Watershed Plan, no date (Box 2, Volume 12)
      For Land Management Unit Four. Includes description of unit, degree and cause of erosion and vegetative depletion, land use and status, land management activities, objectives of a program for the unit in order of priority.
    - Supplement of Sub-Watershed Plan, no date (Box 2, Volume 13)
      Prepared by E.A. Nicholson.
    - Work Report, Soil and Erosion Survey, no date (Box 2, Volume 14)
      Classification and distribution study of various soil found throughout Unit Four. Supplemented by three maps. (2 copies)
    - Work Report, Conservation Survey, 1936, 1938 (Box 2, Volume 15)
      Wepo Valley Water Spreading Area and Cisco Alec Farms, Pinon. 88 pp., 2 maps.
    - Construction Program, 1937 (Box 2, Volume 16)
      Description and recommendations for improvement of watering facilities of Unit Four.
    - Tabulation of Population, District Four, no date (Box 2, Volume 17)
      Arranged according to community area, consumption groups and number of people. Gives individual names.
    - Tabulation of Prairie Dog Infestation, no date (Box 2, Volume 18)
  - Subseries 5, Unit Five, ca. 1937
    Located in extreme southwestern corner of Navajo reservation, Unit Five is drained by the Dinnehbitoh, Oraibi, Polacca, Jeddito, and Corn washes; and includes Talani Lakes. It likes between the 110°30' and 111°30' meridians of longitude and 35°00' and 36°00' parallels of latitude.
    - Engineering Report, April, 1937 (Box 3, Volume 19)
      Prepared by Allen Stammo. General description of unit, topography, geology, vegetation and erosion control and water spreading projects. 6 maps and sketches.
    - Agronomy Branch Report, February-March,1937 (Box 3, Volume 20)
      Prepared by E.A. Nicholson. General description of land; summary of soils and erosion factors; and agriculture needs and practices. 58 pp., 1 map.
    - Planting Possibilities Report, April, 1937 (Box 3, Volume 21)
      Prepared by D.W. Dresbach. Deals with types and methods of planting to aid in soil conservation. 19 pp., V, 1 map
    - Plan of Conservation Operations, no date (Box 3, Volume 22)
      A listing, in order of importance, of conservation projects and a tabulation of costs involved. 25 pp., 36 maps.
    - Report of Extensive Biology Survey, February-March, 1937 (Box 3, Volume 23)
      Prepared by W.W. Morris. Survey of biological factors (rodents, predators, insects, and plant diseases) causing damage to range and agricultural land. Also includes recommended projects to alleviate conditions, and a plan for refuge for migratory waterfowl. 38 pp., appendix, 6 maps and diagrams.
    - Forestry Report, April, 1937 (Box 3, Volume 24)
      Prepared by D.W. Dresbach. Survey of existing stands of trees and their conditions, as well as an outline of forest improvement. 31 pages, appendix.
  - Subseries 6, Unit Six, 1937
    Exact geographical area of Soil Conservation Unit Six is not delineated
    - Planting Possibilities Report, July, 1937 (Box 3, Volume 25)
      Prepared by Gale Monson. An outline of types of plants best suited to soil conservation, and suggestions as to what areas should be planted. 16 pp.
  - Subseries 7, Unit Seven, 1937
    Land Management Unit Seven is located in the south-central part of the Navajo Reservation and comprises some 924,082 acres.
    - Engineering Report, September, 1937 (Box 3, Volume 26)
      Prepared by Allen Stamm. Besides offering a general description of the unit, this report delves deeply into climatological data, erosion control and "water spreading" projects; and carefully outlines a proposed work plan. 18 pp.
    - Agronomy Branch Report, July, 1937 (Box 3, Volume 27)
      Prepared by A.E. Nicholson. A detailed report on agricultural practices in area claimed both by Navajos and Hopi. Agricultural conditions as well a thorough improvement plan are outlined. 34 pp., plus charts and map.
  - Subseries 8, Unit Eight, ca. 1936
    Comprises some 1,424,083 acres, and includes the Kayenta-Monument Valley region, as well as Chilchinbito area.
    - Engineering Report, September, 1936 (Box 3, Volume 28)
      Prepared by C.J. McCash. The survey includes surveys conducted at Kayenta, Devehotso, Oljetoh, and Segihotsosi Farms areas. Detailed data on precipitation, runoff factors, drainage ways and erosion control projects.
    - Range Management Report, Monument Valley, August, 1936 (Box 3, Volume 29)
      Prepared by D.C. Anderson. Outlines range conditions, distribution and type of livestock; and suggests methods of range improvement. 38 pp., 5 maps, 4 tables.
    - Range Management Plan, Kayenta Demonstration Area, November, 1936 (Box 3, Volume 30)
      Prepared by W.V. Turner. Delves into condition and values of land, range management objectives and general policies regarding restocking of area. 16pp., 3 charts, 2 maps.
    - Report of Sociological Survey, Monument Valley area, no date (Box 3, Volume 31)
      A survey of population as related to land utilization and agriculture. Means of livelihood and percentage of income gained through livestock raising and farming is tabulated. 17 pp.
    - Forestry Report, Mounument Valley, 1936 (Box 3, Volume 32)
      Prepared by G.A. Herion. Detailed survey of "bearing woodland and timber stands." Available usage of pinon, juniper, oak and various pine is recounted, as are methods for improving and conserving timber. 18 pp., 1 table.
    - Report on Planting Possibilities, 1936 (Box 3, Volume 33)
      A study in range vegetation and planting to control runoff and improve agricultural yields. 9 pp., 2 sketches, 1 map
    - Extensive Faunal Survey, no date (Box 3, Volume 34)
      A tabulation of the kinds and numbers of rodents, predators, and fur-bearing animals found throughout the unit. Includes suggestions for controlling those which damage rangeland, as well as conserving the more valuable species.
  - Subseries 9, Unit Nine, (Missing)
  - Subseries 10, Unit Ten, 1936-1937
    Land Management unit 10 is located approximately in the center of the reservation; and lies between 109°15' and 110°00' longitude and 35°45' and 36°30' latitudes. The area includes Canyon de Chelly.
    - Agronomy Report, 1936 (Box 4, Volume 35)
      Prepared by A.G. Webber, 1936. A general description of geography, physiography of unit, with a detailed study of land improvements designed to check erosion and improve agricultural and range land. 28 pp.
    - Study Group Report, Engineering Division, January, 1937 (Box 4, Volume 36)
      Includes sections on geography, physiography, present condition of agriculture, recommended agriculture developments, water-spreading and erosion. 14 pp., 3 charts.
    - Suggested Construction Program for Land Management, April, 1937 (Box 4, Volume 37)
      Prepared by Paul Phillips. A suggested construction program based on reports of the Land Management Survey and information from other sources. 16 pp., 3 folding charts.
    - Approved Construction Work, May, 1937 (Box 4, Volume 38)
      Prepared by Paul Phillips. An approved construction program, based upon priority and availability of funds.
  - Subseries 11, Unit Eleven, August, 1936
    - Forestry Report, August 6th, 1936 (Box 4, Volume 38a)
      Submitted by Dearl B. Beach. 23 pp., illus.
  - Subseries 12, Unit Twelve, (Missing)
  - Subseries 13, Unit Thirteen, (Missing)
  - Subseries 14, Unit Fourteen, 1936
    This area lies on the southeastern section of the reservation, near the Mesa de los Lobs and extends to the eastern break of the Chuska Mountains.
    - Biological Report, June, 1936 (Box 4, Volume 39)
      Prepared by Paul Phillips. Detailed analysis of fauna found throughout this unit. Crop-pests, forest, and range plants were studied in cooperation with agronomy, forestry, and range management.
  - Subseries 15, Unit Fifteen, (Missing)
  - Subseries 16, Unit Sixteen, (Missing)
  - Subseries 17, Unit Seventeen, ca. 1937
    Located in the south-central portion of the Navajo reservation Unit Seventeen lies between 35°36' of latitude and between 109°15' and 110° of longitude.
    - Engineering Report, no date (Box 4, Volume 40)
      Prepared by W.H. Berry. Includes general description of unit, analysis of erosion, agriculture, waterspreading, and outlines various types of corrective engineering projects.
    - Range Management Report, November, 1937 (Box 4, Volume 41)
      Prepared by W.R. McKinney. General description of existing range condition, as well as an outline for corrective measures. 35 pp.
  - Subseries 18, Unit Eighteen, 1936-1938
    Embraces the area within 35°15' and 36°15' latitude and 109°15' and 108°30' longitude- or roughly astride the Arizona-New Mexico border.
    - Engineering Report, September-November, 1936 (Box 4, Volume 42)
      Prepared by C.J. McCash,. Report on geographical and geological conditions of the unit. It details present and projected agricultural methods, as well as outlining recommendations for construction and maintenances of soil conservation projects. 79 pp., 2 maps, 4 charts.
    - Range Management Reports, March, 1938 (Box 4, Volume 43)
      Submitted by D.D. Anderson. This report deals mainly with livestock water. Listed are all existing wells, springs, and water holes, including areas for improvement. 2 reports, approximately 80 pp. combined, 4 tables.
    - Forestry Report, December, 1936 (Box 4, Volume 44)
      Prepared by G.A. Herion, 23 pp.
    - Sub-Watershed Plan, May, 1938 (Box 4, Volume 45)
      Prepared by J.H. Provinse. Outlines proposed control measures to check erosion and conserve water potential. 51 pp., appendix, 1 map.
- Series 2: Miscellaneous Reports and Maps, ca. 1935-1941
  - A Report on the Rio Grande Watershed with special reference to soil conservation problems, November, 1936 (Box 4, Volume 46)
    Prepared by Rio Grande District staff. 48 pp.
  - Sub-Watershed Plan for Hopi Land Management District, 1936 (Box 4, Volume 47)
    Prepared by Soil Conservation Service and Bureau of Indian Affairs. 34 pp., 3 charts.
  - Conservation Survey of Wepo Valley, 1936-1938 (Box 4, Volume 48)
    Waterspreading area and Cisco Alec Farms, Pinon, Arizona. Work Report. Prepared by H.F. Johnson. 7 pp.
  - Range Management Plan, Steamboat Demonstration Area, 1936 (Box 4, Volume 49)
    Prepared by W.V. Turner,. 22 pp., charts, 1 map.
  - Map, Land Management Unit Four, no date (Box 4, Volume 50)
    "Hopi Wood Use."
  - Fort Defiance- Bonita Creek Flood Control Plan, November, 1941 (Box 4, Volume 51)
    Prepared by Division of Planning,. 13 pp., 1 map, 15 photos.
  - Range Management Plan, Mexican Springs Demonstration Area, April, 1938 (Box 4, Volume 52)
    Prepared by T.L. Heggie. 23 pp., 1 map.
  - Range Management Plan, Marino Lake Demonstration Area, May, 1938 (Box 4, Volume 53)
    By L.L Young. 14 pp., 1 map.
  - Range Management Plan, Ganado Demonstration Area, August, 1935 (Box 4, Volume 54)
    By R.V. Boyle. 10 pp., 2 charts, 1 map.